Dorothy Dehner
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Business and Financial Papers, 1940-1985, Series 3:; (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  - Agreement to Sell Sculptures by David Smith (unfilmed), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Handwritten Receipt and Authentication of David Smith Painting (unfilmed), 1985 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Photograph of David Smith Work with Authentication by Dorothy Dehner (unfilmed), undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Writings, 1920, 1951-1987, Series 4:; (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  Series consists of the writings of Dorothy Dehner, including articles, poems, lectures and speeches, and other pieces, as well as some writings of others. Writings document some of the influences on Dehner's art, some of her ideas about art in general and certain works in particular, and some of her other creative and more scholarly endeavors, as well as some instances of the scholarly interpretation of her own work by others.
  Found is extensive material, including various drafts, proofs, and reprints, relating to her essay on John Graham, which was initially written as a foreword to Graham's Systems and Dialectics of Art re-issued by Johns Hopkins Press in 1971, but was first published as an article in the art journal, Leonardo, in 1968. (Related material can be found amongst correspondence.) Also found are research material (correspondence - mostly copies - and printed material) and drafts of Dehner's essay on David Smith's work, "Medals for Dishonor," which was published as an article in Art Journal in 1977, in addition to a draft of a piece on first meeting Smith for Art in America.
  Dehner's other writings on art include notes and copies of various speeches and lectures given at the Artists Club and the Cummer Gallery of Art, among other places; various statements on art, including remarks on the Menorah, a plan of work, and a short piece on the series of paintings, Life on the Farm; and contributions to catalogs for others, including ones for Joel Levy and Joan Paul. Dehner's poems include one she wrote in high school, manuscripts of two that were published in the journal, Tracks, and ones that she wrote for her stepdaughter and granddaughter. Other writings include notes taken during a stay in the hospital in 1933, and later reflective and memoir pieces, written for her granddaughter, upon the death of Marian Willard, and on other occasions.
  Writings of others include a copy of a letter by David Smith and a piece he wrote on his work, "Medals for Dishonor" (which could very well be part of Dehner's research material for her essay on this work); a copy of a 1953 speech on "the origins of sculpture" given by David Smith; poems by Herman Cherry; and manuscripts for various essays on Dehner, two of which appeared in catalogs accompanying Dehner exhibitions at Rutgers University in 1984 ("Dorothy Dehner: Life and Work" by Judith McCandless) and Baruch College in 1991 ("Dorothy Dehner" by Joan Marter).
  Writings are typically arranged in rough chronological order. The writings of others are arranged in files at the end of the series.
  - Poems (Reel 1269), 1920, 1952-1975 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Notebook, Hospital Notes (unfilmed), 1933 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Notebook also contains some drawings and sketches that may or may not relate to the hospital notes.
  - Artist Statements (Box 4)
    - (Reel D298), undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - (unfilmed), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Lectures and Speeches (Box 4)
    - Speech Given at Sculpture Forum at the Artists Club (Reel D298), circa 1959 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Notes on Lecture Given at Parsons School of Design (Reel 796), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Lecture Given at Cummer Art Gallery (unfilmed), circa 1969 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Notes on Speech Given at College Art Association Meeting (unfilmed), undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - On John Graham (Box 4)
    - "Memoir of John Graham" (Box 4)
      - (Reel D298), undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - (unfilmed), undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Drafts of Foreword to System and Dialectics of Art (Reel 796), 1966-1971, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
    - Proof of Foreword to System and Dialectics of Art (Reel 796), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Drafts of "John Graham: A Memoir" (Box 4)
      - (Reel 796), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - (unfilmed), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Proofs of "John Graham: A Memoir" (Reel 796), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Reprints of "John Graham: A Memoir" (Reel 796), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - [Notes on John Graham?] (unfilmed), 1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - On David Smith (Box 4)
    - Draft of "David Smith: First Meeting" (Reel D298), circa 1966 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Research Material on "Medals for Dishonor" (Box 4)
      - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - (Reel 3482), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - (unfilmed), 1940, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - "Medals for Dishonor: The Fifteen Medallions of David Smith" (Box 4)
      - (Reel 1269), circa 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - (Reel 3482), circa 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - (unfilmed), circa 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 79-80)
  - Reprint of "Plexiglas Relief for the Great Southwest Industrial Park, Atlanta, Georgia, U.S.A." (unfilmed), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Draft of Foreword to Catalog for Joel Levy (Reel 1372), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - "Remembering Marian" (unfilmed), 1985 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - "Of Life and Death" (Reel 1269), undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Biographical Writing, undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - "For Melanie" (unfilmed), undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - "A Response to the Work of Joan Paul" (unfilmed), undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Writings of Others (Box 4)
    - Copy of David Smith Letter and Text and "Medals for Dishonor" (unfilmed), 1942 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Copy of Speech Given by David Smith, Norman, Oklahoma (Reel 1269), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Poems by Herman Cherry (Reel 1372), 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - "Dorothy Dehner: Life-Line in Sculpture" by Judith McCandless (Reel 1269), 1974 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - "Dorothy Dehner: Life and Work" by Judith McCandless (unfilmed), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - "Dorothy Dehner" by Joan Marter (unfilmed), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 93)
- Printed Material, 1940-1987, Series 5:; (Boxes 4-5; 0.6 linear feet)
  Series consists of printed material collected and accumulated by Dehner, including exhibition catalogs, announcements and invitations, clippings, art catalogs, programs, and miscellaneous printed material, pertaining to her own work, the work of David Smith, and, to a limited extent, the work of others. Clippings on Smith concern his death in 1965 and posthumous alterations to the painted surfaces of some of his outdoor sculptures (at the hands or through the negligence of Clement Greenberg, one of the executors of Smith's estate), which was a source of some controversy in the art world of the mid-1970s.
  Printed material is typically arranged in alphabetical order by type.
  - Art Catalogs (unfilmed), 1970s (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Clippings on Dorothy Dehner (Box 4)
    - (Reel 796), 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - (Reel 1269), 1954, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - (unfilmed), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Clippings on Smith (Box 4)
    - (Reel 1269), 1959-1976 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - (Reel 1372), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - (unfilmed), 1965-1976 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Clippings on Lucille Corcos Levy (unfilmed), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Clippings (unfilmed), 1978-1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations (Box 4)
    - (Reel D298), 1952-1965 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - (Reel 796), 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - (unfilmed), 1970-1987 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Posters (Box 4)
    - (Reel D298), 1956, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - (unfilmed), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations for David Smith (unfilmed), 1940, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations for Others (Box 4)
    - (Reel 1372), 1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - (unfilmed), 1976-1984 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (Box 4)
    - (Reel D298), 1941-1966, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 112-114)
    - (Reel 1269), 1971-1977 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - (unfilmed), 1965-1987, (3 folders) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 1-3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for David Smith (Box 5 (hol))
    - (Reel D298), 1971 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 4)
    - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 5)
    - (Reel 1372), 1973, 1976 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 6)
    - (unfilmed), 1946-1974 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Others (Reel D298), undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5 (hol))
    - (Reel 1269), 1977 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 9)
    - (unfilmed), 1979, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Printed Material on Dorothy Dehner (unfilmed), 1952, 1964-1980 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Printed Material on David Smith (unfilmed), 1973 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Programs (Box 5 (hol))
    - (Reel D298), 1947 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 13)
    - (Reel 1269), 1972 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 14)
    - (unfilmed), 1983 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Book Excerpts on David Smith (Reel 1269), undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 16)
- Art Work, undated, Series 6:; (OV 1; 1 item)
  Art work consists of two undated etchings. One is an abstract by Dehner, which she gave, presumably as a gift, to Garnett McCoy, former Curator of the Archives of American Art. The second one is of portraits of artists done by one another on one etching plate. Artists include Lucille Corcos by Dehner, David Smith by Lucille Corcos, Adolph Gottlieb by Edgar Levy, Edgar Levy by Esther Gottlieb, Dorothy Dehner by Adolph Gottlieb, Esther Gottlieb by David Smit. A cat and alligator were drawn by Edgar Levy in the middle border. The etching is 91/100 and was printed by Michael Kirk on the Charles Brand Press in the Parsons School of Design Studios and seems to have also originally belonged to Garnett McCoy.
  - Etching, Artists' Portraits(unfilmed), undated (Box OV 1)
  - Etching, Abstract(unfilmed), undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 17)
- Photographs, 1930s-1986, Series 7:; (Box 5; 0.1 linear feet)
  Series consists of photographs of Dehner, her friend and mentor John Graham (taken by her in the Brooklyn apartment she shared with David Smith), and her second husband Ferdinand Mann (featured with others, including Fiorello LaGuardia, Arshile Gorky, and Henry Knight, at the opening of the W.P.A. Art Gallery), as well as photographs of Dehner works from the 1950s (assembled in an album or portfolio of "Recent Works") and some later works. Also found is an abstract photograph taken by David Smith circa 1934, one of several he created using the technique of double exposure.
  Photographs are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Photographs of John Graham and Art in His Collection (Reel D298), 1930s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Abstract Photograph by David Smith (unfilmed), circa 1934 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Photograph of Ferdinand Mann at Opening of W.P.A. Art Gallery (Reel 1372), circa 1938 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Art Work, Album and Loose Photographs (Reel D298), 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 21-22)
  - Photograph of Dorothy Dehner at Yaddo (Reel 1372), 1971 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Dehner Exhibition (unfilmed), circa 1985 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Photograph of Dorothy Dehner with Her Art Work (unfilmed), 1986 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Art Work [taken at Dehner's home] (unfilmed), 1986 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 26)
    Includes photograph of Dorothy Dehner with unidentified woman.
  - Photograph of Art Work by John Graham (unfilmed), undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 27)